<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://posmikdc.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://posmikdc.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-04-15T19:58:40+00:00</updated><id>https://posmikdc.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Applying to Biostatistics Ph.D. Programs</title><link href="https://posmikdc.github.io/blog/2023/biostats-phd-admit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Applying to Biostatistics Ph.D. Programs"/><published>2023-04-25T14:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-25T14:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://posmikdc.github.io/blog/2023/biostats-phd-admit</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://posmikdc.github.io/blog/2023/biostats-phd-admit/"><![CDATA[<p>I just finished my application cycle for Ph.D. programs in Biostatistics and I am lucky enough to begin my doctoral studies at Brown in the fall. When I was preparing my application, I profited greatly from other folks sharing their experiences, especially <a href="https://www.khstats.com/blog/phd-apps/">Kat Hoffmann</a> and <a href="https://www.simonpcouch.com/blog/2021-03-15-apply-to-stats-grad-school/">Simon Couch</a>. Being a first-generation college student, a community college grad, and an international student; paying this advice forward is important to me. If you are getting ready to apply, I hope my experiences can help you out. Please don’t hesitate to reach out to me at <a href="mailto:posmikdc@gmail,com">posmikdc@gmail.com</a>. If you are a non-traditional applicant, I would be happy to glance over your work (availability permitting).</p> <h2 id="some-preliminary-disclaimers">Some Preliminary Disclaimers</h2> <p>Please note that this post represents my opinions (subjective!) alone. My situation–more on that later–is quite different from a <em>traditional</em> applicant (more on that later). In that sense, please take all opinions with a grain of salt. When stating/ recalling facts, I will do so to the best of my availability. Please reach out to me if you find any factual inaccuracies.</p> <h2 id="my-background">My Background</h2> <p>I think it is important to start out describing my background. I graduated from a large public state school with degrees in Economics, Business Analytics, and a minor in Mathematics. Before that, I completed an Associate’s degree in Business Administration at a community college within the University of Cincinnati system. After graduation, I briefly worked at an economic research consultancy focusing on energy economics. Coming out of undergrad, I was dead set on pursuing a Ph.D. in Economics, so when I was offered a pre-doc position at the <a href="https://urbanlabs.uchicago.edu/labs/energy-environment">Energy &amp; Environment Lab at the University of Chicago</a>, I jumped on it. I worked at the intersection of causal inference and machine learning there, although my work was not very technical (i.e. I wasapplying existing methods to new data sets rather than developing new statistical methods). Throughout this time, I became more and more fascinated with Statistics. After 8 months, I decided to leave the E&amp;E Lab and start my studies as a non-degree-seeking graduate student at the University of Chicago. The rationale was that I needed some more rigorous coursework (e.g., analysis) under my belt to be a competitive candidate for Ph.D. programs in (Bio-)Statistics.</p> <p>If you want a more comprehensive overview, check out my CV <a href="https://github.com/posmikdc/cv/blob/main/cv.pdf">here</a> (Note that this is my current CV, not the one I submitted).</p> <h3 id="my-interests-and-goals">My Interests and Goals</h3> <p>Though I feel like this changes by the minute, I am broadly interested in the intersection of causal inference and statistical network analysis. In particular, I care about causal inference in high-dimensional networks, non-parametric and assumption-lean methodology, and dynamic treatment regimes. Ultimately, I would like to apply my work at the interface of public health and climate, helping policymakers make more informed decisions in response to environmental disasters and global warming.</p> <p>With respect to my post-Ph.D. goals, I think the following breakdown (currently) describes it best.</p> <ul> <li>A career in academia: 55%</li> <li>A career in a public/ think tank role: 43%</li> <li>A career in private industry: 2%</li> </ul> <h3 id="why-biostatistics">Why Biostatistics</h3> <p>When it came down to sending out my applications, I ended up applying exclusively to Biostatistics Ph.D. programs (with the exception of one program). Here is why:</p> <ul> <li>Biostatistics allows me to be a statistician while maintaining my applied interest in public health and environment</li> <li>Biostatistics programs tend to be much more causal inference focused than traditional Statistics Ph.D.’s</li> <li>Biostatistics programs are highly interdisciplinary, something I really value</li> </ul> <h3 id="my-weaknesses">My Weaknesses</h3> <ul> <li><strong>Undergraduate background</strong>: I majored in neither Statistics or Math in undergrad. Although my coursework was certainly not <em>inadequate</em>, I know that competing with math and stat majors from Ivy+ universities was going to be challenging. On that note, my undergraduate institution is not particularly academically renowned in my fields of study.</li> <li><strong>Recommendations</strong>: This is a mixed bag but I actually didn’t end up with a single UChicago recommender. Only one of my recommenders was a Statistician (+1 Economist, +1 Operations Researcher). Fun fact: I was going to end up getting a recommendation from a UChicago prof but I did so poorly on a midterm, we decided that wouldn’t be wise lol (So keep your head up!). One thing that was devestating to me is that I actually did not get a letter from the UChicago lab I worked at (I would’ve had to stay longer, by lab policy). This was a huge disadvantage.</li> <li><strong>Graduate coursework</strong>: I was enrolled in a full-time non-degree-seeking program taking graduate coursework, but that is still not the same as an MS in Statistics.</li> </ul> <h3 id="my-strengths">My Strengths</h3> <ul> <li><strong>My Publication</strong>: I have a single-author peer-reviewed publication from undergrad. Though the paper doesn’t propose any new statistical methodology, it does focus on the application of some interesting methods in novel ways and applies to data. I think that really helped me. Moreover, the professor who supervised this thesis (an Economist) wrote me a kick-ass letter of recommendation.</li> <li><strong>Research Experience</strong>: Ironically, my application profile was flipped when compared to most traditional applicants. Usually, applicants to (Bio-)Statistics Ph.D.’s are math/stat undergrad majors from very respectable institutions with little to no research experience. My profile was the opposite of that. I had almost two years worth of full-time research experience but a lack of formal preparation. I think my research background in causal inference and ML (in addition to my publication) were my strongest assets.</li> <li><strong>Grades</strong>: I had excellent grades throughout my undergrad. During my first quarter at UChicago, I got two “A-“ and one “Pass” (Injury related). The latter is respectable though certainly not outstanding.</li> <li><strong>Leadership Experience</strong>: I do think that my leadership roles–e.g., founding a successful data science / social justic org in undergrad–was a big bonus on my application.</li> </ul> <h2 id="the-application-process">The Application Process</h2> <p>I went into this application cycle with the mentality of “giving it a shot”. I was fully prepared to get rejected by all programs because I thought my strengths did not quite outweigh my weaknesses. With that in mind, I applied to both masters degrees (Only in Canada for funding and personal reasons) and my <em>top</em> Ph.D. programs. Here is the list of the places I applied to:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Type</th> <th>Institution</th> <th>Program</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>Ph.D.</td> <td>UC Berkeley</td> <td>Biostatistics</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Ph.D.</td> <td>University of Washington</td> <td>Biostatistics</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Ph.D.</td> <td>Columbia</td> <td>Biostatistics</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Ph.D.</td> <td>Harvard University</td> <td>Biostatistics</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Ph.D.</td> <td>Yale University</td> <td>Biostatistics</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Ph.D.</td> <td>University of Michigan</td> <td>Biostatistics</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Ph.D.</td> <td>Johns Hopkins University</td> <td>Biostatistics</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Ph.D.</td> <td>University of Chicago</td> <td>Data Science</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Ph.D.</td> <td>Brown University</td> <td>Biostatistics</td> </tr> <tr> <td>M.Sc.</td> <td>University of British Columbia</td> <td>Statistics</td> </tr> <tr> <td>M.Sc.</td> <td>McGill</td> <td>Biostatistics</td> </tr> <tr> <td>M.Sc.</td> <td>McGill</td> <td>Statistics</td> </tr> <tr> <td>M.Sc.</td> <td>University of Toronto</td> <td>Statistics</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>I applied to the UChicago Data Science Ph.D. mostly because I was currently working at the UChicago Data Science Institute and I knew a good amount of the faculty. I applied to Masters only in Canada because (1) I was eligible for German government funding in Canada but not the U.S., (2) For personal reasons, and (3) Overall cost and quality of life. Additionally, I was a finalist for a full-ride leadership-based scholarship at McGill.</p> <h3 id="preparation">Preparation</h3> <p>I started preparing my application materials very early, around June, because I knew I had a ton of time over the summer (as opposed to zero time in the fall). One thing I did that made life significantly easier for myself and my recommenders is to start a GitHub repository called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">grad-apps</code> that contained everything. At the time I was writing my applications, this repo was public, so all my recommenderes and mentors could have easy access to it. It is now private (and will remain private) for privacy reasons.</p> <p>That being said, I am happy to share how I set it up. Here is content of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">README.md</code> file:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Hi! If you are reading this, I want to thank you for helping me in my graduate school application process. Thank you so much for your support. 

* You can navigate this repository via the branches
* Please access my most up-to-date CV and this `README` via this main branch 
* Each program I am applying to has a corresponding branch with the following format: [institution]-[type]-[program], e.g., "uw-phd-biostatistics" for the University of Washington's Biostatistics Ph.D. 
* Since this is a public repo, please note that you do not have editing access. If you have comments/ suggestions, please do not directly edit these materials. Instead, please use the [comment function](https://docs.github.com/en/pull-requests/collaborating-with-pull-requests/reviewing-changes-in-pull-requests/commenting-on-a-pull-request#) and/or let me know separately. 

Please note that I update this repo every time I make local changes. If you have any questions at all, please reach out to me via email at posmikdc@uchicago.edu or via cell at [xxx]. 
</code></pre></div></div> <p><strong>TLDR</strong>; Create a separate branch for each program you’re applying to and let everyone know.</p> <h3 id="my-application-materials">My Application Materials</h3> <p>I have decided to post all my application materials for Brown’s Biostatistics Ph.D., the program I will be attending in the fall. It should go without saying that you should <strong>under no circumstances</strong> copy and paste from my materials. That being said, as a first-gen student, I know that sometimes it is difficult to find good examples of SOP’s, personal statements, and CV’s.</p> <embed src="/Users/posmikdc/Documents/assets/posmikdc.github.io/assets/pdf/brown-biostatistics-phd.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="600px"/> <p>Now, I will provide some commentary on these application materials:</p> <ul> <li></li> </ul> <h3 id="interviews">Interviews</h3> <h3 id="the-waiting-game">The Waiting Game</h3> <h2 id="decision-time">Decision Time</h2>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="biostatistics"/><category term="admission"/><category term="phd"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My experience applying to Ph.D. programs in Biostatistics]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://posmikdc.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://posmikdc.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://posmikdc.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>